Finding Aid for Justin W. Leonard Papers 1937-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Justin W. Leonard Papers 1937-1975
Leonard, Justin W., 1909-1975.
Conservationist, professor of natural resources at the University of Michigan. Professional files, including correspondence, speeches, and newspaper clippings; letters to his wife, 1943-1946, while in military service stationed in the Solomon Islands during World War II; and photographs.
85253 Aa 2
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Justin W. Leonard (donor no. 5755 ) and came to the library in 1975-1976.
The collection is open for research.
Besides being a University of Michigan professor of zoology and natural resources, Dr. Justin W. Leonard was also an internationally recognized aquatic entomologist, conservationist, and ecologist.
Born on October 28, 1909 in Moulton Iowa, Leonard was the son of Ira Jay Leonard and Edna Wilkinson Leonard. His father, a field botanist all his life, taught school until he reached his mid-thirties, when he turned to farming. He and his wife remained on the farm in Moulton until they died.
Justin Leonard received his AB degree in 1931 from Grinnell College, Iowa, where he majored in zoology and chemistry. He continued his studies of zoology at the University of Michigan, where he obtained his AM degree in 1932 and Ph.D. in 1937. From 1932-34 he worked for the University of Michigan as a museums aide, lecturer, and Hinsdale Scholar. In 1936, Leonard married Fannie A. Divelbess.
In 1934, Leonard went to work as a research biologist for the Michigan Department of Conservation at the Institute for Fisheries Research in Ann Arbor. From 1939-43 he was the director of the Hunt Creek Experiment Station near Lewiston. However, World War II interrupted his career. He joined the Army, where he served as a medical entomologist, and over the course of the war moved from First Lieutenant to Major. In 1943, he was the Post Entomologist at Fort Jackson, South Carolina. He went on to be the Commanding Officer of the 446 Medical Comp. Unit, Guadalcanal, Solomon Islands, from 1944-1945, and from 1945-1946 he was the Island Malaria Control Officer.
After the war, he returned to work at the Institute for Fisheries Research. In 1951, Leonard was promoted and he went to work at the Michigan Department of Conservation headquarters in Lansing as Chief of Research and Development.
In 1964, Leonard's career took a new course when he accepted a position on the University of Michigan School of Natural Resources faculty. From that date until his death in 1975, he was a professor of zoology and natural resources and a research associate for the Museum of Zoology. In 1964-65 he was Acting Chairman of the School of Natural Resources Department of Fisheries and when that department merged with the Wildlife Department in 1965, he became Chairman of the joint Department of Wildlife and Fisheries until 1967. At that time he became Chairman of the Department of Resource Planning and Conservation, a position he held until his death. His major professional and research interests were in integrated management of natural resources, fishery biology, and aquatic and medical entomology.
Leonard participated in many professional societies during his lifetime. Listed alphabetically they are as follows: The American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Fisheries Society, the American Institute of Biological Societies, the American Institute of Fishery Research Biologists, the American Society of Limnology and Oceanography (of which he was vice-president in 1951), the Ecological Society of America, the Entomological Society of America, the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters (of which he was president in 1962), the Michigan Natural Resources Council (of which he was chairman in 1958-59), Phi Sigma and Sigma Xi (both honorary scientific societies), the Society of Systematic Zoology, the Soil Conservation Society of America (for which he served on the outdoor Recreation Committee from 1963 until he died), and The Wildlife Society (of which he was president in 1956 and served on the Leopold Award Committee in 1967).
Other appointments and honors are as follows: the Alumni Achievement Award of Grinnell College in 1961 with Fannie, the Board of Directors of the Michigan Rehabilitation Corporation from 1957-60, the Governor's Committee on the Control of Botulism from 1963-64, Governor's Designee of the McIntyre-Stennis Fund from 1962-64, Lecturer for the Department of Forestry at Michigan State University from 1957-64, the National Academy of Science (NAS) committee on Biology and Renewable Resources in 1966, the NAS/NRC Committee on the Control of the Imported Fire Ant in 1967, a member of the study team to evaluate the proposed Rampart Canyon Dam Project on the Yukon River in Alaska in 1964, Special Consultant to the U.S. Public Health Service from 1956-1966, Wallace Memorial Lecturer at the University of Louisville in 1956, and Visiting Professor in Japan in 1969 speaking on management of natural resources. He was also selected for inclusion in Leaders in American Conservation.
Alone or with a colleague Leonard authored more than seventy bulletins and journal articles (more than fifty with his wife Fannie), some technical and some for the layman, and a number of books: Mayflies of Michigan Trout Streams with Fannie, Conserving Natural Resources with S.W. Allen, and The Rampart Dam and Economic Development of Alaska with Dr. Stephen Spurr.
The Leonard collection consists of thirteen linear feet of materials, most of which is correspondence, both personal and professional. There are also biographical and genealogical information, clippings, speeches, research notes, photographs, printed materials, and miscellaneous writings. The collection has been arranged into the following series: World War II service; Professional Correspondence; Topical Information; Topical files; Organizational/People file; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Leonard, Justin W., 1909-1975.; Natural resources--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Leonard, Justin W., 1909-1975.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.; University of Michigan. School of Natural Resources.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- World War II service
  World War II Service consists of letters written to his wife from the Pacific Theater as well as information on the Solomon Islands and the Malaria Control Program there. The World War II letters are an interesting account of Leonard's experiences, reactions, and feelings during the war, though until almost the end he could not write much about his work because of the censors. Most of the letters are to his wife.
  - Letters to his wife and others from the Pacific Theater 1943-May 1946, 26 folders (Box 1)
  - History of the Solomon Islands (Box 1)
  - Malaria Control, Solomon Islands (Box 1)
  - Army (various) (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence
  Professional Correspondence is arranged chronologically and covers the period from the 1930s to 1975.
  - Undated 1930s-1962, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - 1963-1975, 13 folders (Box 2)
- Topical Information
  Topical Information is a miscellanea of clippings about Leonard, some speeches, various writings, and University of Michigan materials.
  (published, notes, speeches, etc.)
  - Clippings of colleagues (Box 2)
  - Clippings undated, 1930s-1970s, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Drummond Hunt (humorous description) 1960 (Box 2)
  - Huron Mountain Wildlife Foundation printed materials 1971-1975 (Box 2)
  - Leonard, Jay and Edna-biographical information (Box 2)
  - Lovejoy, Parish S.-Biographical material, clippings, writings (Box 2)
  - Michigan Hunters and Anglers Association-speech of Cassell Pursell May 1952 (Box 2)
  - Research report notes (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Speeches undated, 1940s-1970s, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Trip 1971 to Tahiti, Australia, S.E. Asia, India, Europe-description (Box 2)
  - TV appearance--account in UM News October 15, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Writings (miscellaneous)
    - Miscellaneous writings (Box 2)
    - Leonard, Justin and Fannie-Mayflies of Michigan Trout Streams book reviews (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook (Box 2)
    - Reprints of articles (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Biological Station-humorous writings (Box 2)
    - Department of Biology- 1961-1962 Annual Report (Box 2)
    - School of Natural Resources
      - 1964 Dean selection committee and merger of Fisheries and Wildlife-notes and printed material (Box 2)
      - 1965 Department of Wildlife and Fisheries-printed material (Box 2)
      - 1967 Department of Conservation-printed material (Box 2)
      - 1973 Leonard as substitute Dean-notes and printed material (Box 2)
  - Vitae of students (Box 2)
  - Whitlock, Stanley C. (former assistant chief of the Game Division of the Michigan Department of Conservation)-eulogy by Leonard (Box 2)
  - Wilkinson, John (great-grandfather of Edna Wilkinson Leonard, Justin's mother)-his story (Box 2)
- Topical files
  Topical Files consists of files from Leonard's organizational affiliation, also speeches, lectures, and travel materials.
  - American Fisheries Society (Box 3)
  - American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists (Box 3)
  - Bibliographies and biographical sketch (Box 3)
  - Assistant and Associate Deans Committee (Box 3)
  - Awards (Box 3)
  - Committee: University Land Committee (Box 3)
  - Community Leaders Conference (Box 3)
  - Conservation Education Association (Box 3)
  - Conferences (Box 4)
  - International Association of Game, Fish and Conservation Commissioners (Box 4)
  - Landscape Design Study Course (Box 4)
  - Michigan Academy of Science (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Science
    - Biology and Renewable Resources panel (Box 4)
    - Committee on the Imported Fire Ant (Box 4)
  - News clippings (Box 5)
  - Pond Sites memo (Box 5)
  - Sigma Xi (Box 5)
  - Speeches and Lectures (Box 5)
  - TV Lecture Series (Box 5)
  - Trip to Japan (Box 5)
  - Xi Sigma Pi (Box 5)
- Organizational/People file
  major topics only included in this listing
  The Organizational/People file details Leonard's work with environmental and conservation organizations such as the American Fisheries Society. There is considerable with the previous two series.
  - Correspondence 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - American Fisheries Society (Box 6)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences (Box 6)
  - American Institute of Fishery Research Biologists (Box 6)
  - Bureau of Commercial Fisheries (Box 7)
  - Conservation Foundation (Box 7)
  - Ecology (Box 7)
  - Eastern Michigan Nature Association (Box 7)
  - Ecological Society of America (Box 8)
  - Entomological Society of America (Box 8)
  - Environment (Box 8)
  - Great Lakes Basin Commission (Box 8)
  - Great Lakes Research Conference (Box 8)
  - Huron River Watershed Council (Box 8)
  - Hunter Attitudes (Box 9)
  - International Biological Program (Box 9)
  - International Fisheries (Box 9)
  - Lagler, Karl F (Box 9)
  - Michigan Association of Conservation Ecologists (Box 9)
  - Michigan Academy of Arts, Sciences, and Letters (Box 10)
  - Michigan Conservation Commission (Box 10)
  - Michigan Department of Natural Resources (Box 10)
  - Michigan Natural Resources Council (Box 10)
  - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (Box 10)
  - Michigan Water Resources Commission (Box 10)
  - National Research Council (Box 11)
    - Committee on Pest Biology (Box 11)
  - National Academy of Science (Box 11)
  - National Wildlife Federation (Box 11)
  - North American Wildlife and Natural Resources Conference (Box 11)
  - Organization for Tropical Studies (Box 11)
  - River Ecology Symposium (Box 12)
  - Soil Conservation Society
    - Committee on Outdoor Recreation (Box 12)
  - Sport Fishing Institute (Box 12)
  - Spurr, Stephen (Box 12)
  - Trout Unlimited (Box 12)
  - Van Coevering, Jack (Box 13)
  - Water Resources Commission (Box 13)
  - Wildlife Management Institute (Box 13)
  - Wildlife Society (Box 13)
  - Administration of National Parks and Equivalent Reserves (Box 13)
  - American Fisheries Society (Box 13)
- Photographs
  Photographs consist of portraits and other photos accumulated during his career.
  - Field work, including animals (Box 13)
  - Groups, formal (Box 13)
  - Groups, informal (Box 13)
  - Staff (Box 13)
  - Self and family (Box 13)
  - "Ecology: Man and the Environment" (Box 13)
    (descriptive information only)